<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Thomas Van Hoey</title>
<link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>This is Thomas Van Hoey&#39;s personal website.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Xu Zhang</title>
  <link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Zhang_Xu.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This project will, for the first time, provide a cross-linguistic comparison between English and Mandarin Chinese of highly grammaticalized directional particles such as ‘up’ and ‘down’ in English, and ‘shang’ (上) and ‘xia’ (下) in Mandarin, to convey aspectual meanings of completion or intensification in a parallel verb-particle construction in the two languages (e.g., finish up in English and guan shang in Mandarin). The study investigates changes in the (constraints on) productivity of the already grammaticalized particles (which originally expressed direction) in American English and Mandarin Chinese, with particular attention on the association of register with more or less innovative use.</p>
<p>The project has three primary objectives: (i) to map the semantics and productivity (i.e., their capacity to combine with a variety of verbs) of these grammaticalized particles in American English and Mainland Mandarin Chinese from 1920 to 2020; (ii) to examine the productivity of these particles across different registers, including (for contemporary data) in web-based content, with the goal of understanding the role of register in the innovative use of verb-particle constructions in both languages; and (iii) theoretically, by looking at two unrelated languages, it particle combinations, including the question to what extent highly grammaticalized constructions in unrelated languages show parallelisms in their (post-grammaticalization) development, and whether any substantial differences can be seen as persistence effects from their earlier grammaticalization history.</p>
<p>This study is based on a comprehensive database of verb-particle combinations, drawing from multiple corpora. For English, data is sourced from the Corpus of Historical American English (COHA), the Corpus of Contemporary American English (COCA), and Global Web-Based English (GloWbE). For Mandarin Chinese, data is collected from the Lancaster Corpus of Mandarin Chinese (LCMC), the BLCU (Beijing Language and Culture University) Chinese corpus, and the Leiden Weibo Corpus. The dataset provides a balanced representation of spoken, written, and web-based registers across a 100-year period, spanning from 1920 to 2020.</p>
<!-- [Find more about Sumin Guan here.](https://www.arts.kuleuven.be/ling/qlvl/people/pages/00158381) -->



 ]]></description>
  <category>committee member</category>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>U Antwerpen</category>
  <category>ongoing</category>
  <guid>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Zhang_Xu.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fen Huang</title>
  <link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Huang_Fen.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The intersection between language variation and language complexity is empirically under-researched but hugely important for linguistic theorizing. A pilot investigation in the spirit of the so-called “single meaning” approach – see Gardner et al.&nbsp;(2021), employing spoken English data with corpus linguistic methodology, indicates that grammatical variation (e.g., Give me one vs.&nbsp;Give one to me) does not complicate language production, as choice contexts do not attract dysfluencies (i.e., long pauses and um’s and uh’s). The conclusion diverges greatly from traditional theorizing about grammatical variation and optionality, which is often perceived as suboptimal and complex by linguists. Enlightened by Gardner et al.&nbsp;(2021), the current study aims to conduct more specific and in-depth research by adopting psychological experiments to explore the correlations between linguistic variation and language comprehension/production complexity. This project will extend discoveries by Gardner et al.&nbsp;(2021) and provide empirical data support for comprehending linguistic variation as an omnipresent occurrence in human languages.</p>
<!-- [Find more about Fen Huang here.](https://www.arts.kuleuven.be/ling/qlvl/people/pages/00157540) -->
<!-- needs to checked -->



 ]]></description>
  <category>committee member</category>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>KU Leuven</category>
  <category>ongoing</category>
  <guid>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Huang_Fen.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Xiaoyu Tian</title>
  <link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Tian_Xiaoyu.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Cognitive Sociolinguistics, an enterprise that integrates Cognitive Linguistics and Sociolinguistics, aims to take account of formal, conceptual and lectal dimensions for a more realistic model of language variation. In line with recent development in Cognitive Sociolinguistics, this project aims to provide a multidimensional investigation of Chinese analytic causative constructions from both synchronic and diachronic perspectives. This project is comprised of three work packages. Work package I investigates language-internal (syntactic, semantics) and language-external (variety, genre) factors affecting the alternation of the most frequently used causative markers, i.e.&nbsp;shi, ling, rang and jiao from a synchronic perspective. Work package II provides a diachronic analysis of Chinese analytic causative constructions. Work package III gathers converging evidence from psychological experiments to verify whether the predictions of corpus based statistical models can reflect human speakers’ preference. Given the fact that analytic causative constructions are less well studied than morphological and lexical causatives in general, this project will not only serve as an important reference for studies on Chinese causatives, but also will contribute to the discussion on analytic causative constructions from a cross-linguistic perspective.</p>
<!-- [Find more about Fen Huang here.](https://www.arts.kuleuven.be/ling/qlvl/people/pages/00157540) -->
<!-- link needs to checked -->



 ]]></description>
  <category>committee member</category>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>defended</category>
  <category>KU Leuven</category>
  <guid>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Tian_Xiaoyu.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Meili Liu</title>
  <link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Liu_Meili.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The proposed project provides a synchronic and diachronic study of the ba-construction in Mandarin Chinese. In essence, it is an SOV construction in which the marker ba precedes the object, which in turn is followed by the verb expressing the action affecting the object. Its structure can be represented as “subject + ba + object + verb (+ X)”. The construction is traditionally said to convey the notion of ‘disposal’, whereby ba functions as a disposal marker (or object marker). Against the backdrop of previous literature, the present project, which is based on empirical (corpus-based) qualitative and quantitative analyses, intends to provide a more comprehensive account of the Mandarin Chinese ba-construction. It encompasses three dimensions of study—a synchronic study, a diachronic study and a variationist study. Specifically, I will first design the constructional network to represent the taxonomy and hierarchy of the Mandarin Chinese ba-construction at the synchronic level, and then investigate its diachronic development, especially the change of nodes and links (both taxonomic and vertical) in the constructional network of ba-constructions, such as node creation or loss, node-external reconfiguration of the network and in/decrease in productivity and schematicity within the theoretical frameworks of grammaticalization and diachronic construction grammar. Furthermore, the Mandarin Chinese ba-construction can actually be seen as a kind of differential object marking (DOM), and hence special attention will be paid to the motivation of the rise of the Mandarin DOM, compared to the findings proffered in the literature of cross-linguistic DOM studies. Finally, the variationist study intends to investigate the factors that condition the variation between the ba-construction and the jiang-construction, and between the SOV construction (including a disposal marker such as ba) and the corresponding SVO structure without the disposal marker. This project will shed new light on the vexed issue of the origin of the ba-construction and the motivation of the rise of this Mandarin DOM. Moreover, since Chinese, as an analytic language and without inflectional morphology, is quite different from Indo-European languages, the project will serve as a useful case to check the applicability of the grammaticalization theory and the (diachronic) construction grammar. It may provide new insight into both theories. Finally, the emergence of the disposal construction is regarded as one of the five major changes in the history of Chinese (Wang, 1958). This project may thus advance our understanding of the evolution of the disposal construction in particular and the formation of the Contemporary Chinese language system in general.</p>
<!-- [Find more about Sumin Guan here.](https://www.arts.kuleuven.be/ling/qlvl/people/pages/00158381) -->



 ]]></description>
  <category>committee member</category>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>KU Leuven</category>
  <category>ongoing</category>
  <guid>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Liu_Meili.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ruiming Ma</title>
  <link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Ma_Ruiming.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Ruiming’s PhD project aims to answer the question: Does grammatical optionality (e.g., the witch’s wand vs.&nbsp;the wand of the witch) complicate speech production and comprehension? Using a Mandarin Chinese corpus, she attempts to identify the impact of grammatical optionality on dysfluencies in speech production; on the other hand, she will carry out a psycholinguistic experiment to measure the correlation between grammatical optionality and speech comprehension.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.arts.kuleuven.be/ling/qlvl/people/pages/00157540">Find more about Ruiming Ma here.</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>co-supervisor</category>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>KU Leuven</category>
  <category>ongoing</category>
  <guid>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Ma_Ruiming.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jiayin Zhang</title>
  <link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Zhang_Jiayin.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Thanks to globalization, the presence of Chinese-speaking people in Belgium is growing, and so are Heritage Learners (HL) among them. Due to the influence of the linguistic environment, local languages such as Dutch and French become the first language of Belgian Chinese descendants, while Chinese becomes their Heritage Language (HL).</p>
<p>In the field of HL studies, both identity and motivation are prominent themes (Leeman, 2015; Li &amp; Duff, 2014), and learners’ identity and motivation are closely intertwined (He, 2010; Li &amp; Duff, 2014). However, the majority of research has focused on their static and attribute-like nature, and only a few scholars have paid attention to the dynamic changes and interaction between motivation and identity (Choi, 2018). Since most Belgian Chinese descendants have “bicultural identities” and are “bi(multi)lingual”, their dynamic identity trajectories in the process of learning Chinese is worth investigating.</p>
<p>Therefore, this research project will adopt the theoretical framework of the L2 motivational self-system (L2MSS) and Identity Negotiation Going (INT), and research tools such as semi-structured interviews, quantitative analysis and questionnaires in order to conduct a longitudinal study on the interaction between identity and motivation of Chinese descendants studying Chinese in Belgian Chinese language schools. The project is innovative in that it establishes the context for Chinese HL research in a non-English speaking context, examines the dynamic interaction between identity and motivation, and examines the Chinese HL learning of Belgian Chinese immigrant descendants from the perspectives of culture, psychology, and personal experience. The research attempts to improve academic support for this group and produce helpful recommendations for Chinese HL teaching.</p>
<!-- [Find more about Fen Huang here.](https://www.arts.kuleuven.be/ling/qlvl/people/pages/00157540) -->
<!-- link needs to checked -->



 ]]></description>
  <category>committee member</category>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>KU Leuven</category>
  <category>ongoing</category>
  <guid>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Zhang_Jiayin.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sumin Guan</title>
  <link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Guan_Sumin.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Applying the framework of Probabilistic Grammar and variationist sociolinguistics, this project will probe the alternation between competing Chinese passive constructions marked by bei/rang/jiao/gei/zao. Taking into consideration both language-internal and language-external constraints, I will rely on corpus data, psycholinguistic experimentation and multifactorial analysis techniques to explore how probabilistic grammars constrain variant choice, and the extent to which the conditioning of variation differs across varieties of Mandarin Chinese.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.arts.kuleuven.be/ling/qlvl/people/pages/00158381">Find more about Sumin Guan here.</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>committee member</category>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>KU Leuven</category>
  <category>ongoing</category>
  <guid>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Guan_Sumin.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Yi Li</title>
  <link>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Li_Yi.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Situated in the field of variationist sociolinguistics and research on the probabilistic grammars that regulate variation, this study aims to provide a comprehensive analysis of the language-internal and language-external factors that influence the probabilistic grammars of varieties of Mandarin. More specifically, we are set to examine how the dative alternation in Mandarin is conditioned by various constraints that are syntactic (e.g.&nbsp;constituent weight, NP expression type), social (e.g.&nbsp;regional varieties), stylistic (e.g.&nbsp;spoken vs written) and diachronic (i.e.&nbsp;past vs present). To achieve such objective, the study will follow the paradigm of probabilistic grammar, which is based on the ground that factors influencing speakers’ choice of interchangeable linguistic variants are multifaceted and non-deterministic (cf.&nbsp;Bresnan, 2007; Barnaisch et al., 2014; Theijssen et al., 2013). Meanwhile, we are to adopt a usage-based, empirical method to approach this issue, utilizing large-scale authentic corpora and statistical regression modelling to illustrate the directions and magnitudes of multiple variables governing the Mandarin dative alternation.</p>
<!-- [Find more about Fen Huang here.](https://www.arts.kuleuven.be/ling/qlvl/people/pages/00157540) -->
<!-- link needs to checked -->



 ]]></description>
  <category>committee member</category>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>defended</category>
  <category>KU Leuven</category>
  <guid>https://thomasvanhoey.com/supervision/Li_Yi.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
